[
  {
    " q": "q1",
    "item": "changes1",
    "trail1": "Discover",
    "trail2": "",
    "question": "A fossil is…",
    "correctAnswer": "The remains of a plant or an animal turned to stone",
    "correctResponse": "Correct! Fossils are produced when a plant or animal dies and is quickly buried under sediment, such as sand, mud or particles in water. Over millions of years, the remains are compressed underground and eventually turn to stone.",
    "incorrectAnswer1": "An ammonite",
    "incorrectResponse1": "No, an ammonite is an extinct sea creature that lived millions of years ago - the only reason we know about them today is because of fossil remains of their shells.",
    "incorrectAnswer2": "A model of a dinosaur",
    "incorrectResponse2": "No, a fossil isn't a model, but scientists and museums often use models to help us see and understand ancient creatures.",
    "correctSound": "audio/rooster.mp3",
    "incorrectSound": "audio/Lion.mp3"
  },
  {
    " q": "q2",
    "item": "changes2",
    "trail1": "Discover",
    "trail2": "",
    "question": "You can find fossilised seashells right here in Oxford. Why do you think this is?",
    "correctAnswer": "Parts of Oxfordshire used to be covered by tropical oceans where sea creatures lived",
    "correctResponse": "Correct! By studying fossils, we now know that at different times during the Earth’s history Oxford has been part of an enormous undersea coral reef, been covered in swamps, rainforests and tundra and even been buried under miles of ice.",
    "incorrectAnswer1": "Someone brought them back from a trip to the seaside",
    "incorrectResponse1": "No. The number and variety of shells found buried in Oxfordshire’s rocks tells us that they’ve been here for a very long time – long before humans were around to make trips to the seaside!",
    "incorrectAnswer2": "Some seagulls ate shellfish from the sea and then pooed them out over Oxford",
    "incorrectResponse2": "Nope. The fossilised seashells in Oxford are usually buried deep inside rock where no seagulls could drop them (and seagulls don’t usually swallow the shells anyway!)",
    "correctSound": "audio/rooster.mp3",
    "incorrectSound": "audio/Lion.mp3"
  },
  {
    " q": "q3",
    "item": "fossils1",
    "trail1": "Discover",
    "trail2": "",
    "question": "What does ‘extinct’ mean?",
    "correctAnswer": "All of these animals have died out",
    "correctResponse": "Correct! Animals that are alive today are known as ‘extant’, which means ‘existing’. But when scientists can’t find any more living examples of a certain animal, that animal is said to be extinct. Dinosaurs, mammoths and the dodo are all now extinct.",
    "incorrectAnswer1": "This animal never really existed",
    "incorrectResponse1": "No. You might be thinking of mythical or fairy tale creatures like unicorns or the Gryphon from Alice in Wonderland. The word ‘extinct’ is only used to describe real animals that completely died out, like the dinosaurs.",
    "incorrectAnswer2": "There are very few of these animals or plants left on Earth",
    "incorrectResponse2": "No. Many animals today are at risk of becoming extinct (dying out completely). They are said to be ‘endangered’. This group includes Asian Elephants, Green Turtles and even the House Sparrow in Britain.",
    "correctSound": "audio/rooster.mp3",
    "incorrectSound": "audio/Lion.mp3"
  },
  {
    " q": "q4",
    "item": "fossils2",
    "trail1": "Discover",
    "trail2": "",
    "question": "Why might scientists choose to study coprolites?",
    "correctAnswer": "They want to know what Ichthyosaurs had for their lunch",
    "correctResponse": "Correct! Coprolites often contain bits of what extinct animals ate. Many Ichthyosaur coprolites contain fish scales and bones of smaller Icthyosaurs, which is evidence of what they liked to eat. Scientists who study fossilised poo are called coprologists!",
    "incorrectAnswer1": "They must be very common, so easy to study",
    "incorrectResponse1": "No, they’re actually really rare. Fossils are usually made from hard bits like bones, teeth and horns. But every now and then, if the conditions are just right, soft things like poo can turn to fossils too.",
    "incorrectAnswer2": "They like gross, smelly things",
    "incorrectResponse2": "Not exactly. Scientists might often be interested in weird stuff, but coprolites are so old that they have turned to stone (been fossilised), so they are no longer squishy and they stopped being smelly a long time ago.",
    "correctSound": "audio/rooster.mp3",
    "incorrectSound": "audio/Lion.mp3"
  },
  {
    " q": "q5",
    "item": "variation1",
    "trail1": "Discover",
    "trail2": "",
    "question": "Variation within a species is…",
    "correctAnswer": "When animals of the same type have some small differences between them",
    "correctResponse": "Correct! Differences between animals of the same species – such as eye colour, fur patterns, fin shapes, height and so on – are called variation within a species.",
    "incorrectAnswer1": "When an animal, such as a tiger, is similar to another animal, such as a cheetah",
    "incorrectResponse1": "No. Tigers and cheetahs may be similar because they are both big cats, but they are actually completely different species. Variation would be the small differences between two tigers, or between two cheetahs – but not between tigers and cheetahs!",
    "incorrectAnswer2": "When an animal is sometimes tired and weak and might get killed by a predator, but sometimes is feeling strong enough to escape and survive",
    "incorrectResponse2": "No. Variations are not to do with how an animal is feeling day to day, but to do with the characteristics it has inherited from its parents – things like height, eye colour, fur patterns, fin shapes and so on. But, if it’s lucky, some variations might actually help it to survive!",
    "correctSound": "audio/rooster.mp3",
    "incorrectSound": "audio/Lion.mp3"
  },
  {
    " q": "q6",
    "item": "variation2",
    "trail1": "Discover",
    "trail2": "",
    "question": "By ‘natural selection’ Charles Darwin meant…",
    "correctAnswer": "That animals with characteristics that help them survive will pass on those characteristics to their young",
    "correctResponse": "Correct! If something about an animal helps it to survive it is more likely to pass its characteristics on to the next generation, so some characteristics naturally carry on and some naturally disappear – natural selection!",
    "incorrectAnswer1": "That animals can choose to change their bodies to suit where they live",
    "incorrectResponse1": "No. The changes in evolution are not chosen by animals, they happen because some animals survive long enough to pass their characteristics to their young and some don’t.",
    "incorrectAnswer2": "Breeding animals like pigeons or dogs so that they look how you want them to",
    "incorrectResponse2": "No. Although breeding animals to keep certain characteristics – such as speckled wings in pigeons – is a kind of selection it is not a natural process. In fact, Darwin called this ‘artificial selection’.",
    "correctSound": "audio/rooster.mp3",
    "incorrectSound": "audio/Lion.mp3"
  },
  {
    " q": "q7",
    "item": "adaptation1",
    "trail1": "Discover",
    "trail2": "",
    "question": "Which of the animals on this table is adapted to live in water?",
    "correctAnswer": "Nile Crocodile",
    "correctResponse": "Correct! With eyes and nostrils located on the top of its skull, the Nile Crocodile can rest almost entirely under the water as it waits to ambush its prey.",
    "incorrectAnswer1": "Waxwing",
    "incorrectResponse1": "No. Waxwings are perfectly adapted for life in the air. They fly thousands of miles each year, breeding in the pine forests of Scandinavia and Russia, but returning to the UK each autumn in search of berries.",
    "incorrectAnswer2": "<i>Allosaurus</i>",
    "incorrectResponse2": "No. <i>Allosaurus</i> was a large carnivorous dinosaur that lived around 150 million years ago. Dinosaurs were reptiles which lived on the land. But there were many sorts of reptiles which lived in the sea at the time of the dinosaurs. We call them marine reptiles.",
    "correctSound": "audio/rooster.mp3",
    "incorrectSound": "audio/Lion.mp3"
  },
  {
    " q": "q8",
    "item": "adaptation2",
    "trail1": "Discover",
    "trail2": "",
    "question": "Which feature does <i>Archaeopteryx</i> share with modern birds?",
    "correctAnswer": "A light skeleton.",
    "correctResponse": "Correct. – Like modern birds, <i>Archaeopteryx</i> has a light skeleton that enables it to fly.",
    "incorrectAnswer1": "A long, bony tail.",
    "incorrectResponse1": "No, this is a feature <i>Archaeopteryx</i> shares with its dinosaur ancestors.",
    "incorrectAnswer2": "Three clawed fingers.",
    "incorrectResponse2": "No, this is a feature <i>Archaeopteryx</i> shares with its dinosaur ancestors.",
    "correctSound": "audio/rooster.mp3",
    "incorrectSound": "audio/Lion.mp3"
  },
  {
    " q": "qi1",
    "item": "origin1",
    "trail1": "Investigate",
    "trail2": "",
    "question": "Why did Charles Darwin become world famous?",
    "correctAnswer": "His book was read by a huge and varied audience.",
    "correctResponse": "Correct. <i>On the Origin of Species</i> was read by a huge number of people and was accessible, even for those without a scientific background.",
    "incorrectAnswer1": "He was the only scientist thinking and writing about evolution in the 19th century.",
    "incorrectResponse1": "No. Darwin was a great collaborator and developed ideas with other scientists.",
    "incorrectAnswer2": "He collected more evidence to support his ideas than other scientists.",
    "incorrectResponse2": "No. Darwin did collect good evidence to support his ideas, but this can be said of other scientists too.",
    "correctSound": "audio/desk_bell.mp3",
    "incorrectSound": "audio/bong.mp3"
  },
  {
    " q": "qi2",
    "item": "origin2",
    "trail1": "Investigate",
    "trail2": "",
    "question": "We know that Lucy (<i>Australopithecus afarensis</i>) is more closely related to modern humans than modern apes, such as chimpanzees and gorillas, because:",
    "correctAnswer": "She has adaptations for walking in an upright position.",
    "correctResponse": "Correct. Lucy’s skull, pelvis and limb bones reveal that she walked on two legs.",
    "incorrectAnswer1": "She has hands that were able to grasp tools.",
    "incorrectResponse1": "No. Lucy and modern apes all have opposable thumbs and are able to grasp tools.",
    "incorrectAnswer2": "She has a large brain.",
    "incorrectResponse2": "No. Skull measurements reveal that Lucy didn’t have a significantly larger brain than modern apes.",
    "correctSound": "audio/desk_bell.mp3",
    "incorrectSound": "audio/bong.mp3"
  },
  {
    " q": "qi3",
    "item": "reproduction1",
    "trail1": "Investigate",
    "trail2": "",
    "question": "When we talk about ‘survival of the fittest’, the fittest are:",
    "correctAnswer": "Those individuals that are best able to survive and reproduce.",
    "correctResponse": "Correct. Variation between individuals in a species means that some will be better adapted to survive in their environment and therefore more likely to successfully reproduce.",
    "incorrectAnswer1": "Animals that have the longest lifespan.",
    "incorrectResponse1": "No. An animal doesn’t necessarily need a long lifespan in order to successfully reproduce.",
    "incorrectAnswer2": "Those animals which produce the largest numbers of offspring.",
    "incorrectResponse2": "No. Even amongst mammals there are different reproductive strategies: Humans have few babies, but look after them for a relatively long time, while shrews have many babies, some of which will be better suited to survive than others.",
    "correctSound": "audio/desk_bell.mp3",
    "incorrectSound": "audio/bong.mp3"
  },
  {
    " q": "qi4",
    "item": "reproduction2",
    "trail1": "Investigate",
    "trail2": "",
    "question": "Which of the following <b>isn't</b> a cause of genetic variations?:",
    "correctAnswer": "Your lifestyle. ",
    "correctResponse": "Correct. Your lifestyle, such as how much you eat or exercise, can lead to variation between you and other people, but it does not introduce variation into your genes.",
    "incorrectAnswer1": "Egg and sperm cells carrying unique combinations of genes.",
    "incorrectResponse1": "No. The unique combinations of genes generated through the sex cells of sexually reproducing animals is one of the reasons we all vary in our characteristics.",
    "incorrectAnswer2": "Random mutations in DNA.",
    "incorrectResponse2": "No. Mutations caused by copying errors or DNA damage both contribute to the introduction of genetic variations in living organisms, and are essential to the process of evolution.",
    "correctSound": "audio/desk_bell.mp3",
    "incorrectSound": "audio/bong.mp3"
  },
  {
    " q": "qi5",
    "item": "ancestors1",
    "trail1": "Investigate",
    "trail2": "",
    "question": "What features does <i>Archaeopteryx</i> have that modern birds DON’T?",
    "correctAnswer": "Teeth",
    "correctResponse": "Correct. Teeth are heavy, so they would weigh birds down when they fly. Instead, modern birds have brilliantly adapted beaks to suit what they eat – long and thin to fish worms out of mud; short and stout for cracking nuts… the list goes on. Some birds do have jagged points on their beaks, but not proper teeth like <i>Archaeopteryx</i> had.",
    "incorrectAnswer1": "Feathers",
    "incorrectResponse1": "No. <i>Archaeopteryx</i>, and many dinosaurs, had feathers. We now think that even <i>T. rex</i> had fluffy down and others like the <i>Microraptor</i> used feathers to glide, but <i>Archaeopteryx</i> is one of the earliest to use feathers to fly.",
    "incorrectAnswer2": "Claws",
    "incorrectResponse2": "No. <i>Archaeopteryx</i> had claws on its feet that look like dinosaurs’ feet, but modern birds’ feet look like this too. Have a look at the Shoebill nearby! It does have odd ‘finger’ claws, which most birds have lost, but the Hoatzin from South America still has this feature.",
    "correctSound": "audio/desk_bell.mp3",
    "incorrectSound": "audio/bong.mp3"
  },
  {
    " q": "qi6",
    "item": "ancestors2",
    "trail1": "Investigate",
    "trail2": "",
    "question": "Which of the following best explains why modern horses are much taller than their ancient ancestors?",
    "correctAnswer": "Their environment has changed.",
    "correctResponse": "Correct. Small ancient horses were very good at avoiding predators in their forested environment, but as the environment became more open, larger individuals became more successful because they could run faster and spot predators from far away.",
    "incorrectAnswer1": "There has been an increase in the number of predators.",
    "incorrectResponse1": "No. Small ancient horses had many predators, but were very good at avoiding them in the forested environment.",
    "incorrectAnswer2": "Humans have specifically bred horses with the most useful features. ",
    "incorrectResponse2": "No. The main differences between ancient and modern horses developed long before humans carried out any artificial selection through breeding.",
    "correctSound": "audio/desk_bell.mp3",
    "incorrectSound": "audio/bong.mp3"
  },
  {
    " q": "qi7",
    "item": "selection1",
    "trail1": "Investigate",
    "trail2": "",
    "question": "How might natural selection shape the optimum size for Snowy Owls?",
    "correctAnswer": "Natural selection favours medium-sized Snowy Owls.",
    "correctResponse": "Correct. Most Snowy Owls fall within a very narrow range of sizes – the perfect size to catch a wide range of prey but still have a relatively small demand for energy.",
    "incorrectAnswer1": "Natural selection favours large Snowy Owls.",
    "incorrectResponse1": "No. Large Snowy Owls are disadvantaged because they have a large demand for energy in an environment where food is scarce.",
    "incorrectAnswer2": "Natural selection favours small Snowy Owls.",
    "incorrectResponse2": "No. Small Snowy Owls can only catch small prey and so consume less food per catch than larger rivals.",
    "correctSound": "audio/desk_bell.mp3",
    "incorrectSound": "audio/bong.mp3"
  },
  {
    " q": "qi8",
    "item": "selection2",
    "trail1": "Investigate",
    "trail2": "",
    "question": "What is the main purpose of a peacock’s long and colourful tail?",
    "correctAnswer": "To attract females (peahens).",
    "correctResponse": "Correct. Peahens mate more frequently with peacocks with larger and more colourful tails.",
    "incorrectAnswer1": "To intimidate other males.",
    "incorrectResponse1": "No. Various studies have been carried out and there is little evidence to show that this is the case.",
    "incorrectAnswer2": "To confuse predators.",
    "incorrectResponse2": "No. Many species, particularly butterflies, use bright colours and eyespots to confuse predators but this is not thought to be the case for peacocks' tails.",
    "correctSound": "audio/desk_bell.mp3",
    "incorrectSound": "audio/bong.mp3"
  }
]